<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of humiliation, and the effects of it in relation to the present occasion</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5431</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2507</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12266202</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12266202</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58087</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61433)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58087)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 899:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of humiliation, and the effects of it in relation to the present occasion</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8, 4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Stephens, pseud.: Christianus Socrates. cf. BM.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58087:1"/>
            <head>OF HUMILIATION, AND The EFFECTS of it, IN RELATION TO THE PRESENT OCCASION.</head>
            <p>THE Effects, Succeſs and Conſequents of the moſt ſolemn Acts of Religion are ſomewhat like to thoſe of the Water of Jealouſie, which to thoſe that were Pure produced a Bleſſing, Health and Conception; but to thoſe who were defiled, a Curſe and Corruption: So theſe if duely uſed never fail of a Bleſſing, but if profaned by Irreverence or Neglect, and undue Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58087:2"/>have a ſuitable Succeſs, miſs of the Bleſſing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and beſides, (it may be) meet with ſome Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Judgment; <hi>For this Cauſe,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul, many are weak and ſickly among you, and many ſleep:</hi> And this he ſpeaks of ſuch as ſhall be ſaved hereafter, as appears by what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows; <hi>For if we would judg our ſelves we ſhould not be judged, but when we are judged, we are chaſtened of the Lord, that we ſhould not be condemned with the World:</hi> By which it appears, That thoſe who ſhall not be condemned with the World, are, if occaſion be, and for that very End, that they may not be condemned with the World, often chaſtened of the Lord, with the ſevereſt of Temporal Judgments, even Death it ſelf; and That this may be prevented by judging our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Among thoſe ſolemn Acts of Religion, by the Well or Ill management whereof we may procure to our ſelves a Bleſſing or a Curſe, <hi>Acts of Repentance and Humiliation</hi> are to be reckoned. And ſince the King and Queen have appointed a General and Publick Faſt and Humiliation, <hi>to implore the Bleſſing of Almighty God upon our Forces by Sea and Land, and Succeſs in the War againſt the French King,</hi> it behoves us to conſider well what we do, that we do not provoke a Curſe inſtead of procuring a Bleſſing upon our ſelves and our Forces by it. And we have the more reaſon to conſider well what we do now, if we do conſider our Ways (as the Prophet <hi>Haggai</hi> admoniſhed the Iſrealiſtes in a parallel Caſe) ſince our laſt Solemn Day, which was for Thankſgiving, for a moſt admirable Mercy and Deliverance; for it is viſible to all, That there is a great Alteration in the Courſe of our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs ſince that time. All went before with a ſmooth and proſperous Courſe, beyond all Expectation, even to Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and hath ever ſince gone as untowardly and heavily. I need not mention Particulars; for it is ſo manifeſt, that none can be inſenſible of it, who are not very ſtupid: but it does concern us to enquire at this Time, when we are about to implore the Bleſſing of God upon our Forces, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we have not by ſome Miſcarriage forfeited that Bleſſing of God, which before was with us. For if we have,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58087:2"/>if we do not confeſs the ſame, give Glory to God, and-ſpeedily reform it, we may ſooner provoke a Curſe, than ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Bleſſing by this days work.</p>
            <p>This was fit and neceſſary to be done, were our Faſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any other occaſion, but being upon ſuch an occaſion as this, we have beſides a ſpecial Admonition to do it. <hi>When the Hoſt goeth forth againſt thine Enemies, then keep thee from every wicked thing.</hi> If there be any thing which hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked an alteration of the courſe of our Affairs for the worſe already, if we look not well to it, our Faſting and Praying will not help us. We muſt conſider the Majeſty of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, before whom the greateſt of Princes are but deſpicable Worms: We muſt conſider the greatneſs of that Deliverance he ſo lately gave us; conſider the ſpecial Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations it layed upon us: and then conſider our ways, how we have anſwered the ſame. Which if we do as we ought we ſhall find, that though we kept a Day of publick Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving; yet neither Prince not Prieſt, nor People (the Parliament) have hitherto done any one act of Gratitude toward Almighty God, anſwerable to the occaſion. It is a very good Obſervation. <hi>Non bene ſuceedunt res Humanae, ubi negliguntur Divinae.</hi> Here lies the very root of all our ſlow Proceedings. And becauſe on ſuch occaſions we are not to mince the Matter, but confeſs, and lament the Sins of our ſelves and our fore-fathers, and of our Kings, our Prieſts and our Prophets: I will plainly relate that which all ought to take into ſerious Conſideration.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian Religion reformed from the Abuſes of the Roman Church, is not only allowed, but embraced, and the Profeſſion thereof authorized by the Laws of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo that any Affront, Contempt, or Diſ-reſpect to it, doth proportionately affect the State, and in that which is moſt Sacred. No wiſe man would unneceſſarily do that which might be interpreted a diſ-reſpect to the State and Government of his Country, nor would any wiſe State, though Heathen, endure to be affronted, much leſs in things ſo ſacred as Religion. Yet to that degree of folly and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are many of the very Gentry and Nobility of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58087:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>degenerated, that they not only patiently ſuffer the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the State to be contemned, violated, and prophaned by the baſeſt of the People, but are themſelves, inſtead of being examples of Virtue, the evil Examples of all Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Vice, and Debauchery.</p>
            <p>The ſpeedy Reformation of this, was certainly the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per buſineſs, and great duty of this State; the neglect of it (I doubt not) a great cauſe and provocation of the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and unhappineſs of the late King, and of our ſlow and unproſperous Proceedings, and if it be longer continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and after a ſolemn day of Faſting and Prayer, will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke ſome ſmarter Chaſtiſement. This was a duty, to which our late Deliverance by ſo extraordinary a Providence, did lead us and oblige us; and this had been a reaſonable act of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, But it muſt be confeſſed that it hath not only been neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, but with ſome aggravating Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi>-Day was ſent to the Prince a <hi>Specimen</hi> of a Declaration againſt Debauchery in the Armies, which had been peruſed and approved by ſeveral Perſons of good Ability, both Divines, Lawyers, and Perſons of Quality.</p>
            <p>It was incloſed in a Letter, to this Effect: <hi>Something of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be Publiſhed by your Highneſs, is exceeding neceſſary, would be but a reaſonable act of gratitude to God, who hath bleſſed you with ſo extraordinary Succeſs, would be very grateful, and much endear your Perſon to all good People, would, as I gueſs by experience, not want a good Effect, and would I hope, conduce to obtain yet greater Bleſſings from Almighty God upon your honourable undertakings</hi> And, becauſe the Prince was then full of Buſineſs, about a Week after notice thereof was given to Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming he would put forward ſuch Works, and not ſuffer them to be neglected by multiplicity of Buſineſs, or world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Policy. Some time after it was publiſhed in Print, both alone, and with other Papers under the Title of <hi>the true En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Government, and Miſ-Government of the four laſt Kings, with the ill Confequences thereof.</hi> In one of which, Entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>A Caveat againſt Flattery and Prophanation of ſacred things to ſecular Ends,</hi> were many things ſaid very plainly, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry truly againſt Debauchery. All was dedicated to the King, with a brief Narrative of the cauſes of the unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58087:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>of thoſe Kings, and the Danger of his involving himſelf in their Fate, and participation in their Judgments, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to his own Hand, <hi>March</hi> 18. And ſome time after preſented to ſeveral of the Lords, and many of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            <p>But to this day hath not any thing been done to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or ſo much as mentioned by King, Biſhop, Lord, or any one of the Commons; nor are we yet awakened to any ſence of the Importance of this Matter, though we ſee ſome things, little leſs than predicted in thoſe Papers, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready come to paſs, as particularly the impeding and croſſing our Preparations for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and encouraging the Iriſh. pag. 15. of the Caveat. And I wiſh we ſee not more come to paſs, as we certainly ſhall if we go on in this manner. Can we think that our verbal Thankſgiving can find acceptance with the Wiſe and Righteous God, without acts of Gratitude, when there is occaſion? It would not with a mortal Man, but rather provoke Indignation. Nor can we reaſonably expect our Faſting and Prayers ſhould ever find favour with him without an actual and ſpeedy Reformation; but rather ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate the fault, and provoke ſome great Croſs and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment.</p>
            <p>Sometimes God is pleaſed in the Government of the World, as it were to withdraw himſelf, and wink at the courſes of Men, and let them go on without check or controul; at other times to appear in extraordinary Diſpenſations of his Providence: And this he is now doing not only in theſe Nations, but in a great part of the World. He hath in an admirable manner executed his Judgments againſt the late King, who had filled up the Iniquity of his Fathers by not only courting, but eſpouſing the Babyloniſh Harlot, and when we might have expected ſome ſevere Judgment, gave us a great Deliverance. He gave to the Prince an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Succeſs, but withal, at the ſame time led him to a Temptation and Tryal? whether after ſuch an Army of Men had ſtooped to him, he would dare, in dependance upon that Providence, to encounter a Party of Vicious and debauched Nobility and Gentry; which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58087:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>had he done all had certainly ſtooped to him, he had kept up his Authority; which with a Mixture of Kindneſs, Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and ſuch like encouragements, would by the Bleſſing of God, have made that Army as debauched as it was, entirely at his Service; and might have made things go more ſmoothly in the Parliament than they have done, without any Politick Compliance with any Faction whatſoever. That he did not do it, if it was through Forgetfulneſs, the Fault lies at the Doctor's Door; but if it was upon Politick Conſiderations, he hath ſtumbled at the very ſame Stone at which King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt did, and unleſs he ſpedily extricate himſelf, will be involved in the Fate of that Family. And for the Biſhops, Lords and Commons, the Repreſentatives of the Nation, who have been ſo buſie in ſcuffling for Places and Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or carrying on the Intereſt of ſome Faction or Party, if they neglect to correſpond with the preſent Courſe of God's Providence in Reformation of the Nation by the Gentle Means of Good Laws and Vigorous Execution by the Civil Sword, God will certainly do it by his rougher Ways, of the Sword of War, and caſt out ſuch unprofitable Servants; our extraordinary Mercies will aggravate our Crimes, may fill up our Meaſure, and the Prophanation of our Faſting and Prayer, by neglect of Reformation may ſeal up our Judgments. I am perſwaded God will pull down the Pride and Inſolence of that wicked Man the French King; and great probability there was he would have done it in a great Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by our Hands, had we made our ſelves fit for his Service; but it is now doubtful, whether he will not firſt ſcourge and purge our wicked Generation by that Rod before he throws it in the Fire: For the things which belong to our Peace, ſeem to be hidden from our Eyes, as if we were poſſeſſed with a Spirit of Slumber and Infatuation. <hi>Quos perdere vult Jupiter dementat prius.</hi> If this Solemnity produce no better Effects in our State, it remains only that Private Men look to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, have a care who they aſſociate with, and enter into ſuch Courſes, as 'tis probable Almighty God will Bleſs and Protect them in: and perhaps the Condition of <hi>Londonderry</hi> in their Siege may be more eligible than of the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> in their Liberty, with Licentiouſneſs.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:58087:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I am amazed to conſider the Supine Negligence and Inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of our State in this Reſpect; and the more, when I conſider, that there are ſome among them, who make Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion, and whoſe ſincerity therein I cannot queſtion. Poſſibly ſome may be of ſome other Church or Party, and look upon all the reſt, as ſuch as are without, and therefore are not concerned for them; but this, if it be ſo, is a Miſtake, for they and their Parties, being Members of the ſame Commonwealth, may deſervedly be involved in the Puniſhment of thoſe Crimes, which they neglect to reform in other Members thereof.</p>
            <p>But for thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> how they can magnifie this for the beſt Church in the World, and at the ſame time, with Patience ſee it made a Cage of every Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Bird, I cannot underſtand; for certain it is, That none of the Debauchees do profeſs themſelves to be of any other Church, but all of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and many of them Zealots for it too: and reaſon good, for there they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived at.</p>
            <p>But I cannot mention this Neglect of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in not reforming its own Members, without calling to mind <hi>another Neglect,</hi> by no means to be paſſed over in Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, upon this Occaſion, becauſe the Miſchiefs thereof do ſeem very likely to fall heavy upon us: And that is of Reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Civilizing and Converting the poor <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who ſeem to have been committed to our Care by the Providence of God: For we have for a whole Age at leaſt wanted neither Men nor Means, nor any thing elſe but good Hearts ſenſible of our Duty, for that Servicet. The Souls of that People and of their Anceſtors, may cry to Heaven for Vengeance for that Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. And we may reaſonably fear that God in Judgment, may make uſe of that neglected and deſpiſed People for a juſt Scourge and Puniſhment for it. The Wit of Man in his Proſperity may find out Fine Plauſible Exccuſes; but it is time now to conſider, How far ſuch Excuſes are like to paſs with Almighty God: And certainly it will be more ſuitable to this Occaſion, to lay them all aſide; take the Matter into ſerious Conſideration, and make that one of the Motives of our Humiliation.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:58087:5"/>
            <p>Beſides the groſs Immortalities of the Nation, there are many other matters, which deſerve conſideration: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, that Root of all Evil, <hi>Coveteouſneſs,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable Greedineſs after the things of the World. This, as it deadens the Affections, and averts the Soul from God, ſo it ſo narrows and contracts it that it cannot freely exert its Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for the Publick Good, but is ready upon all occaſions to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice that to its inſatiable Appetite; which I mention here becauſe I take it to be no ſmall Impediment to the courſe of our affairs at this time. But I ſhall ſay no more of it now.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am ſo well known to want no Good-Will either to the State or Church of</hi> England, <hi>that I think an</hi> Apology <hi>for this Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dealing needleſs. The matter it ſelf, in my Apprehenſion, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries its own Apology and Juſtification with it. And he, whoſe Cauſe and Service I have undertaken, is a better Advocate, than ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I my ſelf, or any Man elſe can befor me.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58087:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A POSTSCRIPT.</hi> To the Paper of HUMILIATION.</head>
            <p>THAT Religion and Vertue do greatly conduce to the Weal and Happineſs of Kingdoms, States, and of all Societies of Men, as well as of ſingle Perſons; and Irreligion, Profaneneſs, Vice and Debauchery, to their Diſſolution and Deſtruction, hath been obſerved by Philoſophers and Wiſe Men in all Ages: And that they have both a Natural Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy thereunto, and are moreover often directed by a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Providence of God in concurrence with other cauſes to thoſe Ends, I have both by domeſtict Examples and Reaſons, as far as I thought neceſſary in ſo plain a Caſe, ſhewed in the <hi>Caveat</hi> before mentioned. In which taking notice of the great Degeneracy and Corruption of the Manners of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I alſo ſhewed that our late Extraordinary, though unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, <hi>Deliverance</hi> did in a more ſpecial manner oblige us to a ſpeedy &amp; effectual <hi>Reformation</hi> thereof: And that we could not expect but that the Neglect thereof under ſuch ſpecial Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations would be attended with ſome obſervable Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or Obſtructions in our Councils and the Courſe of our Affairs, as we have ſeen it hitherto fall out. To this our Solemn <hi>Thankſgiving</hi> added a further ſpecial Obligation; and the not doing it thereupon doth beyond all queſtion aggravate the Fault of our Neglect, whereupon I preſumed to repreſent the Caſe briefly in a particular <hi>Dedication</hi> of thoſe Papers to the King. And when we had another Solemn day appointed for <hi>Faſting and Praying</hi> for God's Bleſſing upon our Forces in the Warr againſt the French King, which certainly adds ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Obligation, it was but a reaſonable Proſecution of the ſame honeſt Deſign to note briefly the Neceſſity of making a Publick Reformation a Concomitant of ſuch a Publick Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation. To all this I will now add theſe few Conſiderations:</p>
            <p>They, <hi>who have any real Love to their Country,</hi> be their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what it will, if they will acquit themſelves but like men
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58087:6"/>of ſenſe and reaſon, ought certainly to endeavour the promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch a Publick Reformation, by the promoting of ſome good and Effectual Laws for that purpoſe, even upon Civil Conſiderations, as a thing tending by a natural Efficacy to make the People much better either for Peace or Warr, and for the Common Benefit and Advantage of the whole Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And for an Experiment of the truth of this we need not go far from home, or from our own times. It will be ſufficient but to reflect back, and conſider well the different Morals of the two Parties in our late Civil Warrs, and their different Succeſs.</p>
            <p>And if they have indeed any thing of <hi>true Loyalty</hi> in them (whereof many have made ſo high Profeſſion) this they ought to demonſtrate both by abſtaining themſelves from contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and affronting the Laws and Government of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in things ſo ſacred with all well conſtituted States, as the Religion Publickly profeſſed by them; and by a real and active concern, as they have occaſion, that all others be effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ually reſtrained. If they have no juſt conern it is certain their Loyalty is but a Superficial thing, a meer pretence for ſome deſign or advantage to themſelves: Nor ever did or ever will ſuch Men prove ſteddy to any Government, but baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betray all, and ſacrifice them to their own Intereſt; and therefore are by no means to be truſted by any wiſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, notwithſtanding any Parts or Abilities, for which they ought the more to be ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>And for thoſe who are <hi>Men of Religion,</hi> and more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly thoſe of the Church of England, beſides the Obligations and Conſiderations before mentioned, <hi>the Common Prayers</hi> of the Church which are daily uſed, and in each Houſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as they do afford to them who are there preſent a daily Admonition of their Duty, ſo are they in my apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion a ſpecial and great obligation upon them to it. For to pray that God will be pleaſed <hi>to direct and proſper all their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations to the Advancement of his Glory,</hi> &amp;c. and never ſo much as enterinto any Conſultation for the effectual reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the Abominable Profanation of his moſt holy Name by all ſorts of people throughout the whole Nation, and moſt impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and preſumptuous violation of his Laws; to pray <hi>that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58087:6"/>all things may be ſo ordered &amp; ſetled by their Endeavours that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion &amp; Piety may be Eſtabliſhed,</hi> and never uſe any Endeauours for the ſuppreſſing of ſo common and notorious Impieties in the Nation; What is it but to add Impiety to Impiety, to turn Religion into meer Formality, and inſted of procuring a Bleſſing to help to fill up the Meaſure of our Sins and pull down the Judgments we have reaſon to fear, the ſooner upon us; And the like obſervations may be made upon the <hi>occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall</hi> Prayers and Confeſſions purpoſely compoſed for the late Solemnities.</p>
            <p>And for thoſe, who perhaps may think better of ſome <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate Churches,</hi> certainly they would take it amiſs if we ſhould queſtion whether they do conſtantly Pray for God's Direction and Bleſſing upon this Parliament, or leſs then is expreſſed in the Common Prayers: And if they come not behind in their Prayers, and yet are as backward in their Conſultations and Endeavours, I ſee not how they are one jot more excuſable, but muſt necceſſarily fall into the ſame Condemnation, if not greater for having deſerted the Church and yet be no better.</p>
            <p>And theſe few <hi>Queſtions</hi> I would propoſe to them all, who pretend to be Chriſtians: Whether they can hope for any good ſucceſs in this Undertaking without <hi>God's Bleſſing,</hi> unleſs it be ſuch as God ſometimes gives to wicked men, whom he uſeth for the correction of others? Whether there be not ſuch <hi>Curſed Things,</hi> and <hi>National Sins,</hi> which may provoke him to withdraw his <hi>Preſence,</hi> and withhold his <hi>Bleſſings</hi> from Chriſtians, as well as from others, untill they be removed? Whether there be not reaſon to believe that <hi>this Nation is Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted and defiled</hi> and entangled in ſome ſuch National Sins and Curſed Things, which may obſtruct the Divine Bleſſing? whether their unaccountable flow, or Retrograde <hi>Courſe of our Affairs</hi> (no leſs to be admired than the precedent eaſy Revolution,) may not with reaſon be reduced and imputed to ſome ſuch ſecret cauſe? And whether a diligent <hi>ſearch</hi> into that remoter but moſt prevalent Cauſe, and ſpeedy and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual <hi>Reformation</hi> of what is amiſs, be not the moſt proper buſineſs to begin with, (if we do indeed depend more upon God's Bleſſing, now under ſuch inviting Circumſtances, than
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58087:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon our own ſhallow and ineffectual Policies) to compleat a happy Progreſs of our Affairs?</p>
            <p>This, if it was done to purpoſe, as it eaſily may, and ought to be, would ſoon produce a great Alteration by the Bleſſing of God in the Courſe of our Affairs for the better. Magnanimity, and Courage is the part and duty of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, as much as of an upright Judge or a Souldier: and if we will ever ſhew it, now is the time. If we baſely fear the loſs of a few debauched Miniſters, Gentlemen or Souldiers, we ſhall really loſe a far greater Number of much better men, and be enſlaved and betrayed, as we well deſerve, by the Company we chooſe: whereas by a generous doing our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty we ſhould better ſecure them better'd by reformation to our Party.</p>
            <p>POſſibly, in the Peruſal of this Paper, ſome who are moſt attentive to the Importance of the Matter, may over-look other things, and think it very good and honeſt; but theſe muſt be Men who have ſome reliſh of ſuch things But others, who are not much affected with that, will be apt the more to regard the Form, and cenſure it for rude and inſolent; and that I am well pleaſed they ſhould do, and as ſeverely as they will: For I know no better way to convince them of a Fault of their own, than to make them judge themſelves in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of another. For If I be rude by plain-dealing with my Fellow-Creatures for their Good, who are perhaps but a little above me in ſome petty, accidental, tranſitory Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, what are they who are not only more rude toward the State, but impious againſt their Creator, or can behold ſuch Rudeneſs and Impiety without any Cenſure, or Endeavour to reſtrain it? Muſt I be cenſured for breaking the Laws of Man, or but of Civility, and out of a good Deſign? And it is equal then that others ſhall be permitted in impudent Contempt of the Religion of the State, and impious violation of the Laws of Almighty God? <hi>Therefore thou art inexcuſable, O Man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt; for wherein thou judgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf. And thinkeſt thou, O Man that judgeſt, — and doſt the ſame, that thou ſhalt eſcape the Judgment of God? Or deſpiſeſt thou,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
